<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<plan>
  <metadata>
    <track_id>add-detached-actor-observability</track_id>
    <type>feature</type>
    <status>completed</status>
    <created_at>2026-05-26T00:00:00Z</created_at>
    <updated_at>2026-05-26T06:22:48Z</updated_at>
    <description>Add scoped running-time observability and terminal result queries for detached bash and detached delegate actor tasks.</description>
    <commit_mode>manual</commit_mode>
    <validation_mode>yield-gap-loop</validation_mode>
    <validation_granularity>final_phase</validation_granularity>
    <gap_loop_round>9</gap_loop_round>
    <execution_mode>sequential</execution_mode>
  </metadata>

  <gap_loop_repairs>
    <repair id="R1" round="1" status="DONE">
      <description>Align observability query wire entries and default retention values discovered during fresh gap-loop review.</description>
      <items>
        <item checked="true">DetachedActorLogs and DetachedActorResult log tails return snake_case wire fields consistently with message tails.</item>
        <item checked="true">Default log and message retention matches documented implementation notes: 512 entries and 256 KiB per buffer.</item>
      </items>
    </repair>
    <repair id="R2" round="2" status="DONE">
      <description>Ensure terminal bash result queries include bounded stdout/stderr tail data by default.</description>
      <items>
        <item checked="true">DetachedActorResult includes recent log tails for completed bash tasks unless callers explicitly disable logs.</item>
        <item checked="true">Regression coverage asserts stdout/stderr tail data is present in completed bash results without include_logs.</item>
      </items>
    </repair>
    <repair id="R3" round="3" status="DONE">
      <description>Capture detached delegate terminal status events in the message observability stream.</description>
      <items>
        <item checked="true">Completed, failed, and cancelled detached delegate actors append system_event status entries before terminal result publication.</item>
        <item checked="true">Regression coverage asserts completed delegate results expose a completion status entry in the optional message tail.</item>
      </items>
    </repair>
    <repair id="R4" round="4" status="DONE">
      <description>Report query-level truncation when retained log or message entries are omitted by caller limits.</description>
      <items>
        <item checked="true">Detached observability queries set truncated=true when limit_entries or limit_bytes omits retained entries.</item>
        <item checked="true">Regression coverage asserts query-level truncation metadata without retention rollover.</item>
      </items>
    </repair>
    <repair id="R6" round="6" status="DONE">
      <description>Preserve RunDetachedBash background-settled compatibility while keeping direct streaming log observability.</description>
      <items>
        <item checked="true">RunDetachedBash direct streaming tasks register with the active orchestrator for background-settled waits.</item>
        <item checked="true">Bound detached fibers can stream stdout and stderr from the bash tool into detached observability logs.</item>
        <item checked="true">Detached bash terminal result output derives from the final tool result instead of an empty assistant tool-call message.</item>
      </items>
    </repair>
    <repair id="R7" round="7" status="DONE">
      <description>Expose detached task creation and observability tools in the default agent toolset.</description>
      <items>
        <item checked="true">RunDetachedBash, DetachedActorList, DetachedActorStatus, DetachedActorLogs, DetachedActorMessages, and DetachedActorResult are no longer filtered as internal-only builtins.</item>
        <item checked="true">Registry and agent tool schema tests assert detached observability tools are visible by default.</item>
      </items>
    </repair>
    <repair id="R9" round="9" status="DONE">
      <description>Rename the public detached bash tool to RunDetachedBash.</description>
      <items>
        <item checked="true">The public builtin schema registers RunDetachedBash and no longer registers DetachedBash.</item>
        <item checked="true">Tool prompt metadata, implementation directory, tests, and track documents use RunDetachedBash for the public tool name.</item>
      </items>
    </repair>
  </gap_loop_repairs>

  <phases>
    <phase id="P1" name="Observability Model And Query Contracts">
      <goal>Define bounded detached log/message/result data model and query tool contracts.</goal>
      <tasks>
        <task id="T1.1" name="Add observability model tests" status="DONE" priority="P0">
          <description>Write failing tests for per-task ring buffer sequencing, source filtering, byte/entry limits, and dropped metadata.</description>
          <acceptance_criteria>
            <criterion id="T1.1-AC1" checked="true">Tests cover stdout/stderr filtering and monotonic sequence cursors.</criterion>
            <criterion id="T1.1-AC2" checked="true">Tests cover rolling discard metadata when retention limits are exceeded.</criterion>
          </acceptance_criteria>
        </task>
        <task id="T1.2" name="Implement detached observability store" status="DONE" priority="P0">
          <description>Add in-runtime structures and helpers for detached log chunks, message entries, result snapshots, and bounded retention.</description>
          <acceptance_criteria>
            <criterion id="T1.2-AC1" checked="true">Detached observability helpers append and query by task id.</criterion>
            <criterion id="T1.2-AC2" checked="true">Overflow behavior preserves newest entries and reports dropped metadata.</criterion>
          </acceptance_criteria>
        </task>
        <task id="T1.3" name="Add query tool contract tests" status="DONE" priority="P0">
          <description>Write failing tests for DetachedActorLogs, DetachedActorMessages, and DetachedActorResult tool schemas and empty/not-found behavior.</description>
          <acceptance_criteria>
            <criterion id="T1.3-AC1" checked="true">Query tools validate missing and unknown task ids.</criterion>
            <criterion id="T1.3-AC2" checked="true">Query tools support source, role, kind, range, and limit parameters.</criterion>
          </acceptance_criteria>
        </task>
        <task id="T1.4" name="Implement query tools" status="DONE" priority="P0">
          <description>Add tools for detached logs, detached messages, and detached terminal results while preserving DetachedActorStatus compatibility.</description>
          <acceptance_criteria>
            <criterion id="T1.4-AC1" checked="true">DetachedActorLogs returns scoped log chunks and cursor metadata.</criterion>
            <criterion id="T1.4-AC2" checked="true">DetachedActorMessages returns scoped message entries and cursor metadata.</criterion>
            <criterion id="T1.4-AC3" checked="true">DetachedActorResult returns terminal state and not-terminal responses.</criterion>
          </acceptance_criteria>
        </task>
      </tasks>
    </phase>

    <phase id="P2" name="Streaming Detached Bash">
      <goal>Make RunDetachedBash observable while running through streaming stdout/stderr capture.</goal>
      <tasks>
        <task id="T2.1" name="Add streaming bash tests" status="DONE" priority="P0">
          <description>Write failing tests showing RunDetachedBash stdout/stderr can be queried while the command is still running and after it exits.</description>
          <acceptance_criteria>
            <criterion id="T2.1-AC1" checked="true">Running RunDetachedBash exposes stdout tail before completion.</criterion>
            <criterion id="T2.1-AC2" checked="true">Running RunDetachedBash exposes stderr tail separately before completion.</criterion>
            <criterion id="T2.1-AC3" checked="true">Completed RunDetachedBash result includes terminal status and bounded stdout/stderr tail.</criterion>
          </acceptance_criteria>
        </task>
        <task id="T2.2" name="Implement streaming sandboxed bash backend" status="DONE" priority="P0">
          <description>Add a streaming process backend that shares permission and sandbox selection semantics with existing bash execution.</description>
          <acceptance_criteria>
            <criterion id="T2.2-AC1" checked="true">Streaming backend appends stdout and stderr chunks with source metadata.</criterion>
            <criterion id="T2.2-AC2" checked="true">Timeout, process error, exit code, and signal are reflected in task result.</criterion>
          </acceptance_criteria>
        </task>
        <task id="T2.3" name="Wire RunDetachedBash to streaming execution" status="DONE" priority="P0">
          <description>Route RunDetachedBash through the streaming backend while keeping task id creation and background scheduling behavior stable.</description>
          <acceptance_criteria>
            <criterion id="T2.3-AC1" checked="true">RunDetachedBash still returns a parseable task id immediately.</criterion>
            <criterion id="T2.3-AC2" checked="true">RunDetachedBash logs are queryable by source while running.</criterion>
            <criterion id="T2.3-AC3" checked="true">Existing detached bash tests continue to pass or are updated to the new observability contract.</criterion>
          </acceptance_criteria>
        </task>
      </tasks>
    </phase>

    <phase id="P3" name="Detached Delegate Messages And Results">
      <goal>Expose recent messages and terminal results for RunDelegateActor detached tasks.</goal>
      <tasks>
        <task id="T3.1" name="Add delegate message observability tests" status="DONE" priority="P0">
          <description>Write failing tests for querying assistant messages, tool call starts, tool results, errors, range cursors, and retention metadata from detached delegate actors.</description>
          <acceptance_criteria>
            <criterion id="T3.1-AC1" checked="true">Tests cover role-filtered assistant message queries.</criterion>
            <criterion id="T3.1-AC2" checked="true">Tests cover kind-filtered tool event queries.</criterion>
            <criterion id="T3.1-AC3" checked="true">Tests verify system prompts and hidden reasoning are not exposed.</criterion>
          </acceptance_criteria>
        </task>
        <task id="T3.2" name="Capture delegate actor entries" status="DONE" priority="P0">
          <description>Add executor/orchestrator taps that append message and tool event entries to the detached observability store for child fibers.</description>
          <acceptance_criteria>
            <criterion id="T3.2-AC1" checked="true">Assistant output, tool call start, tool result, failure, cancellation, and completion entries are captured.</criterion>
            <criterion id="T3.2-AC2" checked="true">Entries are associated with the correct task id and child actor/fiber identifiers.</criterion>
          </acceptance_criteria>
        </task>
        <task id="T3.3" name="Implement delegate result queries" status="DONE" priority="P0">
          <description>Return terminal status, final assistant result, and optional bounded message tail for completed detached delegate actors.</description>
          <acceptance_criteria>
            <criterion id="T3.3-AC1" checked="true">Completed delegate result includes final assistant text.</criterion>
            <criterion id="T3.3-AC2" checked="true">Non-terminal delegate result reports current status unless partial results are requested.</criterion>
          </acceptance_criteria>
        </task>
      </tasks>
    </phase>

    <phase id="P4" name="Compatibility And Verification">
      <goal>Preserve existing detached status, background result events, and recovery semantics while validating the new observability path.</goal>
      <tasks>
        <task id="T4.1" name="Add compatibility regression tests" status="DONE" priority="P0">
          <description>Verify DetachedActorStatus, DetachedActorList, semantic background result events, and existing detached task completion behavior remain compatible.</description>
          <acceptance_criteria>
            <criterion id="T4.1-AC1" checked="true">Existing status/list JSON shape remains compatible.</criterion>
            <criterion id="T4.1-AC2" checked="true">Background result events still emit terminal results.</criterion>
          </acceptance_criteria>
        </task>
        <task id="T4.2" name="Run focused test suites" status="DONE" priority="P0">
          <description>Run the smallest relevant Bun test targets for detached bash, detached status, orchestration, sandbox backend, and terminal projection behavior.</description>
          <acceptance_criteria>
            <criterion id="T4.2-AC1" checked="true">Focused detached actor and sandbox tests pass.</criterion>
            <criterion id="T4.2-AC2" checked="true">No regression is introduced in terminal background result projection tests.</criterion>
          </acceptance_criteria>
        </task>
        <task id="T4.3" name="Document implementation notes" status="DONE" priority="P1">
          <description>Update track analysis notes with final defaults, caveats, and any deferred durability work.</description>
          <acceptance_criteria>
            <criterion id="T4.3-AC1" checked="true">Track analysis documents default retention limits and known tradeoffs.</criterion>
          </acceptance_criteria>
        </task>
      </tasks>
      <confirm protocol="yield-gap-loop" when="after" status="DONE" />
    </phase>
  </phases>
</plan>
